RG 004:005, Barkhamsted Probate Court
Connecticut State Library
Barkhamsted Probate Court records
1825-1977
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Probate Court (Barkhamsted District)
16 cubic feet
Probate record books, 1825-1977; Probate files, 1834-1906.
RG004_005
1913-002 and 2011-087
Historical Note
Barkhamsted, Litchfield County, Town established in 1779
The Barkhamsted Probate District was constituted June 5, 1825, from the New Hartford Probate District. The Barkhamsted Probate District merged January 7, 2003 with the Hartland and New Hartford Probate Districts to form a single New Hartford Probate District. The New Hartford Probate District merged on January 5, 2011 with the Torrington and Winchester Probate District to create the Torrington Area Probate District which serves the municipalities of Barkhamsted, Colebrook, Goshen, Hartland, New Hartford, Torrington, and Winchester.
Town of Barkhamsted, Probate District chronology:
May 1732 - May 1769, Hartford District
May 1769 - May 1825, Simsbury District
May 1825 - June 4, 1834, New Hartford District
June 5, 1834 - January 7, 2003, Barkhamsted District
January 8, 2003 - January 4, 2011, New Hartford District
January 5, 2011 - Present, Torrington Area District
For Probate Court contact information and hours of operation see,.
Scope and Content
Probate record books, volumes 1-20, 1825-1977. Contact the probate court to access record books after Volume 20. See Alternative Form Available note below.
Probate files, 1825-1906. Probate files may consist of estates, conservatorships, guardianships, commitments, and insolvencies. See Alternative Form Available note below.
Inventory control book, 1825-1906 (coverage). Also known as the Godard Digest, it is a list of probate files transferred to the Connecticut State Library. It was compiled at the Connecticut State Library under the direction of State Librarian George S. Godard.
Arrangement
Record books, including Orders & Decrees, are numbered consecutively from 1 to 20. The volume of Distribution Certificates is outside this sequence and is labeled volume 1.
Probate files are arranged alphabetically in one series.
Other Finding Aid
Record Books: Index cards for the record books have been scanned. Ask History and Genealogy staff for assistance.
Record Books: The Probate Estate Papers Index, located in the index corridor adjacent to the History and Genealogy Reading Room, has two parts, a general index covering most of the state, and a Hartford Probate District index covering Hartford and some surrounding towns, 1820-1920. The index cards are arranged alphabetically by individual's last name and first names. The cards have the individual's name, town of residence, probate district, and list of items contained in the estate packet. To request retrieval of an estate packet, copy at least the estate name, file date, and probate district name from the index card. The probate files in Accession 1913-002 are represented in this index.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Probate records -- Connecticut -- Barkhamsted; Probate records -- Connecticut -- New Hartford
Places:
Barkhamsted (Conn.); New Hartford (Conn.)
Alternate Creator:
Connecticut. Probate Court (New Hartford District)
Restrictions on Access
Researchers should first consult use copies when available. See Alternate Form Available Section below.
Accession 2011-087, Record books, 1825-1977, are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Alternative Form Available
Record books, volumes 1-3, 4-8, 10-11, 1825-1924; probate files, 1825-1906; and inventory control book (Godard Digest) were microfilmed by the Genealogical Society of Utah and are available for use in the History and Genealogy reading room or through the.
Provenance
The probate files in accession 1913-002 were transferred to the Connecticut State Library on the following dates (with date span of files): November 26, 1913 (1825-1896); October 13, 1931 (1834-1906). They were interfiled into one alphabetic sequence.
Container List
- Record books, 1825-1977; 12 cubic feet; 2011-087
  - Records, 1825-1832 (Volume 1)
    This volume is New Hartford District
    Note on title page of New Hartford District Volume 3: "Notice: 'It should be remembered the two first volumes of probate records for the District of New Hartford - from AD 1825 to AD 1833 inclusive. - Were directed by the General Assembly of 1834 to be kept in the probate office for the District of Barkhamsted'"
  - Records, 1832-1843 (Volume 2)
    This volume is New Hartford District, 1832-1833, and Barkhamsted District, 1834-1843
  - Records, 1843-1853 (Volume 3)
    On spine: "Letters"
  - Orders & decrees, 1854-1866 (Volume 4)
    On spine: "Records"
  - Records, 1854-1866 (Volume 5)
  - Records, 1866-1887 (Volume 6)
  - Orders & decrees, 1881-1896 (Volume 7)
  - Bonds, 1894-1968 (Volume 9)
  - Orders & decrees, 1896-1917 (Volume 10)
  - Records, 1894-1923 (Volume 11)
    On spine: "Manuscript"
  - Orders & decrees, 1918-1955 (Volume 12)
  - Records, 1923-1941 (Volume 13)
  - Records, 1940-1954 (Volume 14)
  - Orders & decrees, 1953-1972 (Volume 15)
  - Records, 1954-1957 (Volume 16)
  - Records, 1961-1971 (Volume 17)
  - Records, 1969-1972 (Volume 18)
  - Records, 1964-1975 (Volume 19)
  - Records, 1975-1977 (Volume 20)
  - Index card books, 3 books (Box unnumbered box)
  - Distribution certificates, 1892-1930 (Volume 1)
  - Miscellaneous account book, 1885-1921 (Volume unnumbered item)
- Probate files, 1825-1906; 4 cubic feet; 1913-002
  - Adams - Barnes (Drawer 1)
  - Barrett - Carey (Drawer 2)
  - Carter - Case, O. (Drawer 3)
  - Case, R. - Doolittle (Drawer 4)
  - Dowd - Greenleaf (Drawer 5)
  - Grennel - Ingle (Drawer 6)
  - Ives - Mack (Drawer 7)
  - Mallory - Newton (Drawer 8)
  - Olmsted - Roberts, P. (Drawer 9)
  - Roberts, S. - Spencer (Drawer 10)
  - Squire - Wakeman (Drawer 11)
  - Ward - Youngs; Miscellaneous (Drawer 12)
- Inventory Control Book, 1825-1906; T003073
  Index of the two accessions of probate files now merged into accession 1913-002
  Also known as the Godard Digest